the following is a production of Frankie
Freitas and the internet will exam of
holography
[Music]
hello everyone this is Frank D Freitas
and welcome to another week of Holo talk
for the week of November 7th
1999 and welcome to November Our Guest
this week is Dave Hodges and Dave is an
amateur and hobbyist teleographer and
he's going to come on the show and talk
to us a little bit about his setup and
how he got started with photography his
interests and where he's looking to take
holography in the future and this is the
first show of many I hope for the rest
of the season where we can bring amateur
and hobbyist telegraphers onto the show
to talk about the work that you're doing
right in their own homes their garages
their basements or wherever they happen
to have their own studio lab and there's
a lot of very interesting things
happening with amateur and hobbyist
solography right now and it would be a
perfect opportunity to hear what others
are doing across the country and around
the world right here on holotalk and
Dave will be the first person to start
out this series also coming up I have a
special that I'm putting together now
that we're just about a year into doing
laser pointer and diode holography I
thought I would look back over the year
and sort of put everything together into
one concise program to show exactly what
we can do with the laser pointers what
we can do with the diodes and we're
going to take a very interesting look at
the re-emergence of single beam
reflection holography and I think you're
going to find this very interesting show
so there's a number of different things
that have happened over the year that
have been very exciting and I'd like to
put them together into one show and show
you just how far holography has come
with this and like they say what goes
around comes around we're going to take
another look at a single beam holography
which suited was put on the shelf for
many many years but it turns out that it
may see a very interesting re-emergence
for a number of different reasons that I
will cover in in the upcoming show and
I'll try and get that show up next week
but if not next week we'll get it up the
week after so let's move on to the
interview with Dave Hodges I'm not going
to come back on after the interview's
over so I will thank you now for tuning
in and hope you tune in each and every
week here at whole talk when we bring
you news and information about the
fields that we know and love
lasers and holography this is Frankie
Freitas see you next week
hello hello Dave it's Frank defreitis
hey Frank how you doing I'm doing pretty
good
and what part of the country are you in
Dave oh I'm just outside of St Louis
Missouri a town called Saint Charles
okay and I guess you would consider
yourself an amateur hobbyist
photographer right yeah when did you get
started and how did you get started with
holography well let's see it was back I
guess 96. my wife worked at a retail
store and uh they had an old cash
register they were throwing away and I
thought it had a spectrophysics one
milliwatt laser in it and uh I had I had
seen a thing on the Discovery Channel
and I thought well geez I can try this
and I built myself a sand table and all
read about a thousand pages of
documentation and
flew the thing together and started
shooting my heart ramps right did you
get a hologram from using that uh
spectrosythics laser that was in the
cash register yeah I sure did yeah I
sure did as a matter of fact my very
first attempt I I guess I studied it
just good enough to to make a good guess
and the very first two and a half by two
and a half inch plate was a I got a
holograph a little airplane
stealing the kid's toys you know what do
you have your lab set up at in the
basement yeah and what type of table are
you using
well right now I was using a three by
six uh sand table and then I I ended up
oh I doubled the beam back and forth and
I was able to shoot a a hologram for for
Halloween
and uh it was a it was an eight by ten
but it was it was really tough to get
that that set up so a friend of mine
suggested why don't you put a table on
top yeah sand table so I built a five by
ten table
and set it right with real sharp legs
and set it right in the sand oh no
kidding yeah yeah it's uh
I made a made a 90 90 degree grid out of
two by sixes and then set
particle board on top of that
and then pegboard on top of that
and and set the pegboard so that it
straddled the the two by sixes on three
inch Center so basically I have a like a
what do they call it a breadboard table
yes exactly yeah on three inch centers
so it's pretty stable yeah do you use
that pegboard when you set up your
Optical components or are there special
things that you put into this hose now
but I put the 800 blind nuts and on the
bottom of this table oh my goodness uh
yeah what a job my arm got tired uh
but yeah now right now I've got I've got
those 800 nuts on three inch centers
across the whole five by ten table and I
I can just take a quarter twenty bolt in
in a flat piece of wood and just clamp
my Optical components down wow I'd love
to see a picture of that table you don't
have any pictures do you yeah I sure do
like I can put anyone do you have a
scanner or anything uh yeah I do yeah
could you scan one of those pictures and
send it to me I'll put it up on the
website to go with the energy that would
be really interesting to see that table
well as a matter of fact I've got a
couple pictures while I had to I had to
build a jig so I could prop it up on its
side
when I was putting all those blind nuts
in because somebody had to be on the
back and I he pocketed each one of those
and Drew them down with the uh with a
bolt in the washer yeah I've got some of
those pictures up on them okay that
would be good I'll put those up and
people can click on the link and have
the pictures come up and see this table
because I'm very interested it's a very
interesting design well that's a friend
of mine that was a printer the guy that
told me about the uh you use I I we've
talked about this before the guy that
said use Kodak film use Kodak developer
use
Fuji film use Fuji developers do us for
God's sakes you use Russian Film use
Russian developer you know you've worked
with some of the newer materials how do
you find them to work with compared to
when you were working with the agfa
materials
oh gee Frank I shot I shot peace after
peace after peace with no hologram at
all and when I it was there for that
friend of mine I was just telling you
about
and he told me try he goes try that
Russian developer I I call I called
Lithuania and asked him and they told me
they said they were dirty they were
using fm6 for that pfg01 okay and uh
I I started getting Holograms right
after I started using that FM so heck
now whether it was just a fluke or
whether the developer itself I found
that it looked nice I buy the chemical
for mixer myself yeah now what developer
were you using that didn't work with the
Russian well I I tried from d19 but the
when I got a ghost of an image you might
say but it just wasn't what I thought
was
acceptable yeah
I just had Ronnie Anderson from Norway
send me the chemicals for the sm-6 to
try it out so I'm going to be trying
that out too you got it from where
Norway yeah yeah I didn't I didn't want
to buy like a pound of it at a time I
just wanted to try it out and compare it
to the Pyro process so if you tried uh
with the octopus formula actually I
didn't want to buy it in bulk yet I just
wanted to he just sent me enough to make
a leader
oh I see you know just yeah just enough
to make a leader I got a drop of it yeah
just a little bit Yeah because well I've
bought it for enough for maybe five
liters or something like that they'll
sell it in less than a pound yeah I was
just talking to Bill from uh
photographer's formulary today and
they're thinking about making a kit with
the sm-6 developer it's like you can you
can order it just like the jd2 or the
jd3 kit so they're thinking about
putting that together I didn't I didn't
realize that I've been buying the
chemicals just the raw chemical yeah I
think that's how everyone's been doing
it but you're looking to put a uh a
package together send it to the JD
series of developers yeah one one thing
I haven't tried and I'm I've got the
chemicals to do it I just haven't sat
down and mix them up is that that pvu
amidol bleach I haven't tried that have
you talked to anybody that's done that
no no but what bleach are you using with
the sm6 the sulfuric acid and potassium
dichromate okay okay yeah and that that
seems to work I'm getting good result
with it yeah yeah as a matter of fact
I've got a yesterday I sent a hologram
to you in the mail of a rose on this uh
the ceramic Rose and I've got it's in
the mail went on yesterday okay so you
should be getting it there now what are
you thinking about doing with your
business you've uh you've left a
business that you already had to get
started with philography is that correct
yeah that's correct I don't know if it
was the widest maneuver my part but you
know how that goes
but uh well I don't know I have I have
several ideas I think I think that this
thing's going to explode we've talked
about this before Brian uh I think a lot
of people where the airplane was in 1910
i i i i it's an idea that's been around
for a while but I just don't think it's
been exploited what do you think are
some of the things that's going to make
that happen now compared to what wasn't
happening before
well I think the price of lasers are
coming down and of course you've got
that uh that diode that you've been
working on yeah I'd like to get my hands
on one of those yeah uh and and the
blinded with this Russian Film coming in
on the market uh several so we can start
getting consistently good images with
this with this film it seems to be
inexpensive enough to work from the cost
justify to me so to speak so you're
getting very good results with the
slavage film using the sn6 developer and
the potassium dichromate bleach yeah
okay they're acceptable I mean yeah I
finally I find them to be acceptable or
as a matter of fact that Rose I think
you'll be kind of surprised with it it's
uh
got a couple defects but I think that's
from we talked about that also before I
I think it's I tried to I got a real
nice image and then I tried to rush
through five of them just to see how
fast I could do them I think I was doing
them so fast that the glass play still
had heat from my for my fingers on it
yes yes well you can take a look at that
and tell me what you think yeah every
every hologram has the secret to what's
wrong with it if there is something
wrong it's there it talks to you if you
know how to listen to it it'll tell you
exactly what happened I found that these
patterns have you ever seen oh sometimes
you see military footage where people
walk across the floor and then you'll
see they'll use an infrared camera
and and you can see the heat yes okay
you know how that it has kind of a
scintillation type or a more a pattern
that yes well that's a each hologram had
a pattern very similar to that that's
what led me to believe that maybe it was
it was I wasn't letting the settle down
it could be could be polarization that's
possible yeah yeah we'll take a look at
that and we'll see if you've got a
polarized laser we could just rotate
that laser head a little bit and that'll
Disappear Completely
[Music]
yeah let me take a look at that when it
comes through here that's another thing
I'd like to get in the future here is a
polarized laser
I'd like to try that one that you that
you're working on there right well we're
ready to go with those and the only
thing we're waiting to hear uh we have
the Small Business Development Center of
Lehigh University that's helping us get
up and running because
I guess Sam will agree to this that
neither one of us are a real bright when
it comes to business and liability and
things so we just want to make sure that
we're protected and doing everything
legally and uh we just want to make sure
that if anybody gets one of these
systems and they take the diode laser
and decide to eat it for breakfast that
they can't sue us you know that type of
thing yeah exactly because there's a lot
of crazy things out there people drink
paint because now they have the warnings
on the paint can do not drink paint oh
my God someone just sued a Halloween
costume manufacturer because their kid
jumped out of the tree with a Superman
uniform on and he's paralyzed and you
know you gotta watch out for everything
like that so as a matter of fact I was
on the phone with the Food and Drug
Administration for this for what is it
this the center for devices and
radiological Health yeah uh because I'd
like to I'd like to make them display
hologram
model and put them in like like
nightclubs things like that but uh I'm
afraid of somebody getting up there with
a two inches from the beam and staring
into it and then all of a sudden you're
in trouble you know yeah
so what do you want to do with your
business
well you have everything there right now
where you could start running workshops
and having people come in and learn how
to do Holograms that can be a little
lucrative if you've got a uh an area
that hasn't been serviced before by
anyone else doing that well that's that
that's a good that's a good idea yeah
you already know how to do it it's time
to take a few let me let me give you a
couple tips if if you don't mind me
doing so no I don't right you've got old
Rams that you've shot what I would
suggest that you do is take those
Holograms put them into nice little
frames maybe contact your local library
or one of your small private galleries
in the area and tell them you'd like to
put some of your holograms on display
yeah people will come and they'll see
the Holograms and right next to the
Holograms you can have little printed
sheets uh the fact that you run maybe
weekend workshops or something like that
and people will pick those sheets up and
they'll be so fascinated by the
Holograms if they'll want to come in and
make one of their own
that's that's a good idea Brian get you
up and running well that's a good idea
can we talk about this later sure that'd
be great that'd be great I'd be
interested in any any information you
could give me there if you're already
successful making whole grams then
you're to the point where you can show
someone else to be just as successful As
You Are
well that'll be that'd be great yeah
that'd be great have you have you ever
worked have you done much work with film
at all right I have some ad for film but
I've always tried to stay away from it
and the most I ever really use it for is
workshops and tests
you know I I only charge a hundred
dollars for someone to come in and do a
workshop which one's about two and a
half hours or so right and you know to
take up the price of a plate out of that
hundred dollars on top of that takes a
big chunk so I I still use film for the
workshops oh I I see yeah because I was
pricing some some place and I don't
remember if they were those BB play or
if they were if they were the pfgo one
place but they were like for an eight by
ten they were almost fifteen dollars
right yeah yeah you know so I figured
well film's cheap if you if if I'm gonna
do it like a master
well I'll grab a uh
I can grab a piece of glass because I
tried to do a master with with the uh
with a piece of film
and it was it was it was the same little
airplane that I had my first successful
hologram with as a matter of fact and I
put it 10 inches back and I flipped the
plate around it sure enough it's just
hung out there real pretty 10 inches in
front of the play oh yeah so I dropped
another I dropped another plate and
biselected that plane and put another
piece of film there and I I this is a
single being set up
and I've got a white light transmission
hologram out of it
it's not the prettiest one no kidding no
and this was with a single beam yeah
I've got the bean spread to 18 edges
yeah you know so I was able to cover in
in I hit it at an angle of I think I
measured the angle to be 25 degrees
to the uh to the plane of the plate okay
and I was able to get both my plate
holders set up in there
single Beam work is is nice right now
because of the high diffraction
efficiency of the new plates and I'm
going to do a special show on doing
single Beam work because you can even do
image plane Holograms with single beam
well that's exactly what I did yeah
I I got a book homemade Holograms and
they said this is a cheap and dirty way
to do white light transmission hologram
and it's due to the fact that I used
film made made it a bit made my
transmission hologram the white light
transmission hologram a bit grainy
and so I and it was the first one I ever
I was the first one I attempted and
maybe just not because I'm if I did
split beam setup I could use a
collimated reference beam I think they
had to clean it up a lot but I haven't
tried it there's so many experiments out
there Frank oh yeah and nobody could
nobody I don't think could sit down and
try all the experiments that go through
your mind at one you know
yeah at one point with you know the
actual materials were really nice but
they certainly didn't have the
efficiency that the new materials have
so the split being set up was really
nice because you could control the
brightness more and get and get a
brighter hologram as a result of doing
split beam holography but with the new
materials and the diffraction
efficiencies are so high to begin with
there's no need to even set up split
Beam work anymore single beam can give
you just your regular single beam
reflection hologram you can get your
image plane white light transmission
like you just did or an image plane
white light reflection hologram
same result just working with a single
beam Frank one thing I've noticed though
is this when you do your when you do
split Beam work you can you can move
your subject matter further from a plate
as long as you're keeping your beam
distances
close to being equal you'll you'll
you'll have something that appears to be
much deeper because to spread the beam
out that far you lose a lot of light you
know I
I don't know that's just something that
that's just my opinion yeah well believe
it or not with the diode lasers you
don't have to worry about beam pads
anymore because the coherence length is
so long on them I know with this one
that we have here I managed to get out
to 14 feet on the coherence line before
I stop so that's a minimum of coherence
length on that diode is 14 feet did you
set up a set of rails and back that off
a little at a time that's what I'm going
to do I'm going to put a mirror on them
on this
filter on the z-axis and I'm going to
use the micrometer head to actually move
that mirror to see if those fringes go
in and out some people say well I say it
will not
yeah I don't know that's an interesting
thing about coherence length I don't
know if it's a repetition
for your incoherence length and out of
it in it and out of it in it and out of
it in other words does it repeat itself
yeah see John evine I think that's how
he pronounces his last name who wrote
homemade holography and he just did a
two-part Series in popular electronics
and he says toward the end of the
article I believe it's the second one
which is the November issue he thinks
that the uh the laser goes in and out of
coherence every millimeter
but that A millimeter is not it's not
that small that's big A millimeter is
Big that would show up on an object that
would be detectable by the human eye
yeah you'd see that in the final
hologram if that was going in and out
every millimeter or so right but we're
going in in and out every few microns
yeah that wouldn't be detectable by
humans okay and even if it did if it
doesn't show up in the final hologram
what's the deal it wouldn't matter it
wouldn't matter what what are you doing
this for for the end result yes yeah you
know yeah
Vanessa oh another thing that I I found
uh with a with a collimation
a cheap way to collimate a bean is grab
a uh it cost you all at maybe five
dollars
grab a uh
oh a magnifying glass from a drafting
supply house one of those big ones yeah
okay we're working with one color of
light right yeah you don't have that
chromatic uh what is it chromatic
abrasion yes it occurs there so red
light's gonna Focus where red light
would focus anyway yes so so
I found it to work fine no kidding yeah
and it tolerates the beam yeah
why not just drop just drop your your uh
your microscope objective or whatever
you're using the spread the bean your
little positive length put it at the
focal length of the uh
of the magnifying glass and you've got a
collimated bean
wow that's a very good tip I hope people
are listening this far into the show to
pick that up and that's just it's the
thing the thing there's a lot of ways to
save a buck there I mean for
check my polarization I bought a seven
dollar pair of Polaroid sunglasses at
Walgreens yeah I've got a little pen
light I've got a little pin light laser
there and I I it's polarized
and as a matter of fact I tied that down
and shot a postage stamp size hologram
with that and didn't even use a lens
just let the the lens and the legs are
spread out over the length of my table
and I've got a little postage dance side
hologram from that little pin light
laser that was amazed wow
yeah I know there are a few people that
uh and I I've done that myself here I'm
set up for a 30 by 40 centimeter
hologram and I'm not using any of the
collimating Optics in the diode I just
took that lens completely out and that
light is just as beautiful as any
spatially filtered light coming out of
your spatial filter we can't do without
destroying it well that's that's the
point you have to find out with that
particular diode that you're using where
that photodive is located because a lot
of times that photodiode relies on light
reflected back from that collimating
lens in order to control the current
and if you remove that lens you do not
have that reflected light coming off of
that lens going back to the photo diode
anymore the power technology 35
milliwatt that I have even States in
bold capital letters do not even focus
the collimating lens when the laser is
running at full power because that can
blow it out
but fortunately the diode that we're
using in the system that we have the
photodive must be situated so that it
doesn't rely on the reflected light
coming from the collimating one so that
when it's removed it's still giving you
the same output but it's a beautiful
spread and it's almost like it's being
passed through a spatial filter it's
gorgeous uh uh have you ever tried
making your own special filters right no
have you oh yeah I mean
an old wave that I that I had sitting
around
I grabbed the cross light off of it you
know what the cross light on a lathe is
yeah uh it's it's an X in y Pi by axis
okay that's it so you can you're laid
like for turning for turning bats and
and
while making machine screws things of
this major okay well I took it off it
was a small lace and I took this this
cross slide off off the lathe
built myself a little tangent arm that
would pivot up and down and it affixed
it to there so that gave me my z-axis
but really it was kind of an arc it
wasn't an actual z-axis but it worked
and uh then I took my I took and
sharpened a needle under a microscope
punched a hole through a stack of uh
through a stack of
cash oil yeah aluminum foil yeah yeah
well yeah sure and and and then went
through them
and found the one that would let light
through the leaf them out and then I set
that in in the in a in a beam the laser
beam just an unspread laser beam and use
that Airy Airy disc formula yeah and
calculated measured the size of the uh
of the oil and I was able to get down to
like one of my smallest ones it was 25
microns wow so and it
it works fine it takes me all of it but
I can tear tear everything apart set the
set of lens in there set my spatial
filter up
and it takes me maybe five minutes to
adjust the top yeah
well what I'm hoping to do is is to get
it to the point where we're making
beautiful image plane Holograms using
single beam methods that are bright and
not even requiring any lens or spatial
filter at all that'd be great Frank yeah
just the diode itself because basically
according to the spread of the diode you
just place your materials wherever it
happens to be the right amount of spread
for whatever size materials you're
working with
there's some pretty exciting stuff still
coming up yet this isn't all over yet I
think I did fall off my chair when I
found out you could
there was a formula for manufacturing
film Frank
uh I'm looking into that right now as a
matter of fact photographer's formula is
most of the chemicals for that oh really
okay
there's the Fisher Scientific Company
out there okay that I found the
remainder of the chemicals that kind of
cost me a probably a couple hundred
bucks to get the chemicals which is you
know if you if you just scraping by on a
shoestring a couple hundred bucks is you
know like Parish pair of shoes for the
kids yes exactly or what whatever you
know but uh yeah I thought it'd be
easier to get gold out of Fort Knox than
it would have come across a cross a
formula like that yeah I thought that
would be very tightly guarded yeah
that's uh Jeff Blake's work over in the
I think the University of Cambridge in
in England yeah I I as a matter of fact
the very night that I heard that I
pulled that that information off the net
yeah and uh and it started it looks like
it's pretty straightforward yeah yeah
looked like it was all that complicated
I I called my my niece by marriage and
she's going through a chemistry class
and I said this jog my memory this
weight by volume I said that's just so
many grams per 100 grams of fluid
and because if you did you read that
article there where where it gives you
percent weight by volume and it gives
you it gives you weight by volume and I
was a little confused and she said that
that's just uh
well like silver nitrate six percent
weight by volume and deionized water
about six grams per 100 grams of water
oh okay okay but you're actually
measuring the weight of the water and
instead of applying one cubic centimeter
of water weighs a gram that's the way
they set the metric system oh okay so
it's then so you can do a weight by
volume okay okay and uh
so that ought to dial you in close
enough and it looks just like a series
of bass there that you uh that you go
through and
I'm gonna give that a try what was the
most expensive chemical that you found
in the process oh the silver nitrate is
what it was yeah yeah well it's got
silver in it so it's about
about two hundred dollars a pound if
you're gonna buy it by the by the pound
but you can get it uh
let me say I imagine if you bought a
pound of that stuff you'd be able to
make plates for the rest of your life I
would imagine yeah you surely you surely
would
let me get my photographers formula
everything sitting right here let's see
silver
nitrate 100 grams for 68 bucks 100 Grand
would last you a long time yeah because
they'll talk about what pivoting two
milliliters yeah only a four by five
plate
it seemed like in the in the percentage
is only six percent so geez yeah yeah it
seemed like it'd almost last forever
yeah you got plays for the rest of your
life yeah you would it would seem that
way and you know what's neat if you
screw one up you just bathe it take the
Emulsion off put the plate in Clorox it
takes the emotion off and start over
again with a new glass substrate yeah
and it just so happens that I have a
friend that's a Glazer too so I mean I
can probably get spent glass for good
prices yeah
you know so that that's another thing
it's it's the price of this is coming
down with this breakthrough in in Laser
Technology with the diode lasers
it just seems to be something that uh I
think it's going to go for it I think
it's going to go big
I think so too we're looking for some
really big things happening
how soon you think you're going to be
able to release those uh those diode
modules right well what Sam and I want
to do is send an email out to everyone
who's on that list and tell them they
can have one if they sign a release
saying that if they happen to eat one
for breakfast that they can't pursue us
well Frank I'm not going to eat one for
breakfast yeah you never know what's
going to happen there's always something
crazy out there that happens well I'd
like to you know you were talking about
heaven heaven being 14 feet out of
coherence right yeah I'd like to I'd
like to try setting one of those up and
doing a split Bean set up and let it be
14 feet out of length yeah let's see
what you get sure you know I mean if
that's the case
you're it's almost unlimited yes you
know as long as you have vibration
isolation
and what's nice is you don't have to
have a laser as part of the uh isolation
you just need to have whatever happens
to be in the setup and your holographic
plate isolated
yeah yeah that's that's what we were
talking about that before too that was
my understanding I hear a lot of people
that have their laser mounted in another
room yeah and as long as all the optical
components on the table
remain in relative position to each
other
you don't have any problems yeah yeah
but I'll tell you what though Frank that
that table that I built I'm really happy
with it it it does have some drawbacks
to sand because I have to build some of
my own gimbals
to gimbal the uh oh I see yeah the
gimbal the Optics were insane you could
just shove it shove it over and get the
beam to pretty much go where you wanted
it yeah you won't even need Optics when
I'm finished
oh there you go that'll be a thing of
the past there you go that's a that's a
good idea that's a good idea yep but
yeah I'm look I'm I'm looking very
forward to getting my hands on uh on one
of those that you you're you're making
there Frank yes so let me know put me at
the top of the lift or somewhere up
there near the top of the list all right
anything else you want to let anyone
know about before we head out
well not that I can think of uh thank
God for patient wise yeah and all the
kids out there listening don't give up
your dream you know that's that's good
to say you know but yeah that's about
all I can think of I guess we can talk
later huh Frank yeah I'm going to say
goodbye to you now but if you hold on
the line I'll uh I'll pick it up after
we disconnecting the show okay all right
so just don't get it thanks for the
opportunity sure and hold on the line
okay okay see you folks
foreign